<tool id="base_reformat_bedfile" name="Reformat user-provided BED file"  version="0.1.0">
    <description>for use in BayesASE Align and Count workflow</description>
    <macros>
        <import>macros.xml</import>
    </macros>
    <expand macro="requirements"/>
    <command>
<![CDATA[ 
        awk 
            -v FS='	' 
            -v OFS='	' 
            '{print $4,$2,$3,$1}' 
            '$infile' 
        > '$outfile' 
]]>
    </command>
    <inputs>
        <param name="infile" format="txt" type="data" label="Input 4-column BED file to reformat" />
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data name="outfile" format_source="infile" metadata_source="infile"/>
    </outputs>
    <tests>
        <test>
            <param name="infile"      value="align_and_counts_test_data/BASE_testData_BEDfile.bed"/>
            <output name="outfile"   file="align_and_counts_test_data/reformat_BED_file_for_BASE.bed"/>
        </test>
    </tests>
    <help><![CDATA[
**Tool Description**

This tool reorders the columns in a user-specified 4-column BED file. The chrom (chromosome name) and name (name of the feature in the BED line) columns are switched such that the column containing the genic features of interest is column 1 and chrom is column 4.  This allows for the downstream SAM alignments to be reformatted such that the RNAME column in the SAM file contains genic featureIDs in place of chromosome name. 


**Inputs**

The input BED file must contain these columns in the following order:

(1) *Chrom*: The name of the chromosome the genic features are on
(2) *Start*: The start position of the feature on the chromosome
(3) *End*: The end position of the feature on the chromosome
(4) *Name*: The name/ID of the features of interest

Example input BED file:

    +---------------+---------+---------+----------+
    |   chrom       |  start  |   end   |  name    |  
    +---------------+---------+---------+----------+
    |     2R        |  2345   |   2899  | featureA |
    +---------------+---------+---------+----------+

**Outputs**

A 4-column BED file that has the names of the Feature IDs in the first column and chromosome name column last. 


    +---------------+-----------+------------+------------+
    |   name        |   start   |    end     |    chrom   |  
    +---------------+-----------+------------+------------+
    |  featureA     |   2345    |   2899     |    2R      |
    +---------------+-----------+------------+------------+

   ]]></help>
    <citations>
            <citation type="bibtex">@ARTICLE{Miller20BASE,
            author = {Brecca Miller, Alison M. Morse, Elyse Borgert, Zihao Liu, Kelsey Sinclair, Gavin Gamble, Fei Zou, Jeremy Newman, Luis Leon Novello, Fabio Marroni, Lauren M. McIntyre},
            title = {Testcrosses are an efficient strategy for identifying cis regulatory variation: Bayesian analysis of allele imbalance among conditions (BASE)},
            journal = {????},
            year = {submitted for publication}
            }</citation>
        </citations>
</tool>
